In this video, I'm just going to
demonstrate some of the various tools
that you can utilize within Word to
structure and layout your document.
So there are a wide range of formatting
tools within Word and we will cover
certain other ones in other videos.
But the ones I'm going to focus on
here are looking at the cut, copy
and paste and moving text around and
how you can use the sort function
and the find and replace function.
So as you can see, I have an example
letter on the screen in front of me.
And first thing I'm going to
demonstrate is how you can select text.
The first thing to do is you can click
and hold your mouse button and drag your
cursor along till you've highlighted
the text that you wish to select.
Alternatively, you can, if you want
to select just a single word, you
can just double click on the word
and it will just select a word.
If you wanted to select a whole
sentence, so rather than dragging
and hold your mouse button, if you
just click three times, it will
automatically select that whole sentence.
Similarly if I wanted to select a whole
paragraph, I would just click three times
and it would select the whole paragraph.
So if I had a paragraph that I wish to
move around to another position within
the document, I could quite simply,
while it's highlighted, I could click
and hold the mouse button and as you can
see that's allowing me then to move it.
The cursor's moving down and once I
release the cursor it automatically moves
that text to the bottom of the page.
And what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to put that back.
And this brings into play another tool
that you can use, which is the undo tool.
So if you look on the tool bar
at the very top, and you can see
there's a little arrow that points
to the left and that's an undo.
So if I click on that, it will undo what
I've done and place a text back there.
And again, if I wanted to move it back,
rather than having to do it manually again
by selecting it and just click the redo.
Now you can basically go back
as many steps as you want,
until the document was opened.
So if I had done 20 steps, but I
needed to go back to the beginning, I
could quickly undo all of those steps.
So I'm just going to undo
that and move one again there.
So alternatively, to move you can
also cut and copy information.
So if you cut something, it
does exactly what it says.
So if I highlight that text there and
then select the scissors that will
automatically cut that text out of there.
And as you can see, it's left the
full stop, which is why I'm just
going to pop that back in there.
It's sometimes easier to use the select by
clicking three times and I will cut that.
And then I can then move that
to wherever I want to paste it.
So that is very similar.
Exactly the same as the move, you can
cut information from one document or move
information from one document, place it
somewhere else within the document, or
even move it to another open document.
And again, I'm just going to undo
that by - I'll use the shortcut for
the undo, which is Control (ctrl)
and Z, so again, that just places
that back, takes us a step back.
The alternative to that is I can copy,
but obviously a copy does what it says.
It copies the information so
I can use the copy tool there.
Or I can just go Control and C,
now that's copied the information.
Nothing appears to have happened, but if
I click the cursor further down the screen
and then select paste, which I'm going
to use the shortcut Control and V, and
I'll paste that information into there.
So those are some of the basic tools
in relation to cut, copy paste.
And one of the other tools that
I'm going to demonstrate is the
use of the find and replace.
And as you can see, there is a
word "group" that occurs several
times within this document.
And I want to change
that to the word "team".
Now, as you can imagine, I've only
got one letter here, so I could go
through and change each instance
of the word "group" with the word
"team", just by simply highlighting
that and typing the word team.
Alternatively word has a
feature called find and replace.
So if you can imagine if I had a document
with 30, 40, 50 pages and I needed a
change every instance of the word "group"
with the word "team", it would take
quite some time doing it one by one.
Whereas if I use the find and replace
tool that can be done instantly.
So if I click on the replace
button there, that brings up the
find and replace dialogue box.
And what I want to do is I want to replace
the word "group" with the word "team".
And as you can see, that's now going
to look for every instance of the
word "group" with the word "team" so
I can instantly replace all instances.
So I click on that and it's all
done, we've made 12 replacements.
So if I then look through every
instance of the word "group" has
been replaced by the word "team".
Alternative to that is I could
- I'll just close out of that and
just undo what I did - so that's
changed everything back to "group".
If I go on to replace, again.
There may be instances where
a word that you want to change
could be part of a bigger word.
So you have to be careful.
So it may be a case in that instance you
need to do it one at a time, but again,
rather than searching through manually
yourself, you can use the find and
replace tool and so rather than clicking,
replace all, I just click replace.
It will find every instance of
the word "group" and, then give me
the option to change it to "team".
So I click replace and for
every one I'm quite happy.
That's it, it's finished searching
the document, select OK and that has
now changed every instance of the
word "group" with the word "team".
The last thing I'm going to demonstrate is
how you can sort the text alphabetically.
You may not use this very often
within Word, it's something that
you may use more within Excel.
But there may be instances where
you have a list and you wish
to sort that in a certain way.
So what I can do is I can
highlight these list of names here.
And if I click on the A to Z,
that will bring up the sort text
dialog box, and it's sort by
paragraphs, text and, ascending.
There are various other ways that
you can do your sort, but we'll
keep it quite simple on this one.
And we're just going to sort that
ascending, so it's alphabetical,
ascending, click OK, and then that has
sorted all of those names alphabetical.
Again, if I wasn't happy with that, I
can just go up and use the undo button
or the shortcut key, Control and Z.
So that demonstrates some of the
basic formatting tools that you can
utilize to lay out your document.